<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: heroku | David Cramer's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://justcramer.com/categories/heroku/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://justcramer.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-02T14:32:00-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://justcramer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Cramer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Cloud is Not For You]]></title>
    <link href="http://justcramer.com/2012/06/02/the-cloud-is-not-for-you"/>
    <updated>2012-06-02T13:57:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://justcramer.com/2012/06/02/the-cloud-is-not-for-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been a fun year so far. There's been exciting things happening both for me personally, as well as at DISQUS. One of
those things has been launching a new side project, <a href="https://www.getsentry.com">getsentry.com</a>. This is about
it's 4th month running publicly, and it's been doing very well. I wanted to talk a little bit about where it started, and
how quickly it's shifted in the stance of where it's going.</p>




<p>Around Christmas of 2011, and after a lot of prodding by <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/">Craig Kerstiens</a> (of Heroku)
I had finally given in to the pressure of creating a hosted version of Sentry to launch as a Heroku addon. I already knew
Sentry was awesome, as did many others, and this just meant getting something I put a lot of effort into out in front of
so many others. It was very little work to get things up and running on Heroku, and just as easy to setup the addon
endpoints. We started a private beta shortly thereafter, and immediately picked up a bunch of the Django/Python crowd.</p>




<p>From there it slowly, but steadily grew in both customers and data. In fact, for the first couple of months we were able
to survive on just a few dynos and the first tier of dedicated postgres (which was the $200 package at the time). We've
also expanded to cover nearly all popular languages, including PHP, Ruby, Java, and even JavaScript.</p>




<p>A bit further in the background of how I structured the Sentry service:</p>




<ul>
    <li>Two separate apps (www and app)</li>
    <li>SSL everywhere (two certs, two addons, $40/month plus SSL cert costs)</li>
    <li>A minimum of two dynos each ($140/month~)</li>
    <li>Tier-1 dedicated DB (Ronin, $200/month)</li>
</ul>




<p>Now, before I continue, let me say that I thoroughly enjoyed using Heroku. It's a great service, I'm friends with a lot
of people there. Now let's talk about why you shouldn't use Heroku, or the cloud.</p>




<p>Right from the get-go we had a system that had pretty good HA and redundancy, especially due to how Heroku's Postgres
solution works. Unfortunately, we quickly saw the limitations of what both the Postgres and the dynos could handle.</p>




<p>Our first attempt to address this was to add worker nodes (ala Celery) to handle concurrency better. This turned into one
or two additional dynos dedicated to processing jobs, as well as an additional Redis addon. Unfortunately the Redis addon
is completely overpriced, we quickly shifted to pulling up a VM in Linode's eastcoast datacenter instead. This bought us
a little bit of time, but really I'd say we were only given an additional 10% capacity by what should have been a large
optimization.</p>




<p>Another week or two went by, and it was suggested that we get off the Ronin database, and upgrade to the Fugu package (
which bumped up the database cost to $400/month). This did quite a bit. In fact, this let us handle most things without
too much of a concern. A little while down the road, we had a customer sign up who was actually send realistic amounts of
data. More specifically, <strong>not even close to the amount of data Disqus' Sentry server handles</strong>, but about 10x
more than the rest of our customers combined had been sending.</p>




<p>Then shit started to hit the fan.</p>




<p>In no specific order, we started finding numerous problems with various systems:</p>




<ul>
    <li>Redis takes too much memory to reliably queue Sentry jobs.</li>
    <li>Dynos are either memory or CPU bound, but we have no idea how or why.</li>
    <li>The Postgres server can't handle any reasonable level of concurrency.</li>
    <li>We randomly have to spin up 20 dynos to get anywhere in the queue backlog.</li>
</ul>




<p>Given all of that, I made the decision that I was going to go back to using real hardware and managing it myself. I'm
no stranger to operations work, though it's never been my day job. I did however want to do this right, and with the advice
of my coworker, friend, and roommate, <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/sugarc0de">Mike Clarke</a> I decided I'd set these
up properly, with Chef.</p>




<p>About three days into it, and I had learned how to use Chef (I don't write Ruby), brought up two full pluggable
configurations for a db node and a web node, written a deployment script in Fabric, migrated to the new hardware and
destroyed my Heroku and Linode instances. Three days, that's all it took to replace the cloud.</p>




<p>Now you might argue that the cloud let's you scale up easily. <strong>YOU ARE WRONG, IT DOES NOT.</strong> The cloud
gives you the convenience, or more importantly, the illusion of convenience, that you can bring up nodes to add to your
network without giving it much thought. You can do that. You don't ever realistically need to do that.</p>




<p>Almost any company worth a damn can bring online a server within 24 hours, even budget companies. When have you actually
needed turnaround time faster than that? If you did you, maybe you should read up on capacity planning.</p>




<p>The hosted Sentry now runs on two budget servers, one which runs Postgres, pgbouncer, and Redis, the other which runs
Nginx, Celery, memcached, and the Python webserver. The cost for these two machines? About $300/month. When I destroyed
Heroku, my bill was looking to be around $600-700 between Heroku and Linode. Given the numbers we run at Disqus, the
physical hardware should be able to handle no less than 2000% the capacity I was struggling to handle on the cloud.</p>




<p>I'm not saying you can't make use of the cloud. For example, Disqus uses Amazon for running large amounts of map/reduce
work. You know, <strong>elastic computing</strong>, the kind of computing that is inconsistent, unplanned, or generally
infrequent. I'm also not saying you shouldn't Heroku. You should see if it works for you. However, if you ever come up
to me and argue that the cloud is going to fix any problem, I'll make the assumption that you're one of those annoying
kids that runs around screaming MongoDB and Node.js are the answer to all of the worlds problems.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
